

Website: <a href="https://http

Austin, TX

(347) 831-6041 hanafrla@utexas.edu

Profile

PhD Student at University of Texas at Austin and Research Associate at Carnegie Mellon University.

Interested in researching social aspects of modern technology to create a better future, specifically in the context of open source software communities and diverse participation.

Education

University of Texas at Austin; Austin, TX

08/2021 - Present

Pursuing a doctoral degree in Information Studies at the Information School

- Faculty Advisor: Professor James Howison

Carnegie Mellon University; Pittsburgh, PA

08/2016 - 05/2020

B.Sc. Electrical and Computer Engineering

- Minor in Human-Computer Interaction, advised by Professor Laura Dabbish

Research Experience

PhD Student and Research Associate; UT-Austin & CMU

05/2020 - Present

- Current work under professors Dr. Howison and Dr. Dabbish.
 - Designing bot interventions on GitHub seeking to aid first-time contributors
 - Analyzing the unique experiences of BIPOC and trans, non-binary, and genderqueer folk in open source communities
 - Studying the maintainer and organizational influence on project diversity and newcomer retention
 - Analyzing GitHub conversations regarding codes of conduct and governance
 - Designing a panel study to understand OSS work-life balance in order to understand and encourage diverse participation

Research Assistant; Human-Computer Interaction Institute, CMU

09/2019 - 05/2020

- Empirical qualitative study analyzing diversity and inclusion in open source.
- Screened 4000+ users, recruited and interviewed 21 participants, created a coding scheme following grounded theory, and first-authored a paper currently under review.

Research Assistant; Institute for Software Research, CMU

09/2018 - 05/2019

Project validated a new fault-injection framework by retrofitting existing open source applications, developing models of expected application results, and creating a general server in Erlang within Partisan protocol to accomplish hierarchical clustering.

Research Assistant; Electrical and Computer Engineering, CMU

05/2018 - 08/2018

Project involved building and programming a wireless system for neural recording, capable of streaming digitized data to a remote machine for analysis. Project required

system design, PCB sketching and milling, and embedded systems application.

Publications

- Li, Renee, Pavitthra Pandurangan, **Hana Frluckaj**, and Laura Dabbish. "Code of Conduct Conversations in Open Source Software Projects on Github." *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction* 5, no. CSCW1 (2021): 1-31.
- Contribution: Helped analyze and categorize sample of conversations to develop typology on code of conduct conversations

Hana Frluckaj, Laura Dabbish, David Gray Widder, James D. Herbsleb "Gender and Participation in Open Source Software Development" In: Conference on Computer-supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2022)

- Contribution: Interviewed half of participants, transcribed and coded all transcripts, employed grounded theory to compare men and women's career trajectories.

Works in progress

Hana Frluckaj, Huilian Qiu, Laura Dabbish, Bogdan Vasilescu, "Trickle Down Diversity: Company Influence on open source project diversity"

Hana Frluckaj, James Howison, Laura Dabbish, "Cracking the Egg: Understanding Trans Experiences in Open Source Software"

Working Experience

IT Assistant, Institute for Software Research; Pittsburgh, PA

09/2016 - 05/2020

Performed diagnostics and initial troubleshooting tasks, investigated hardware and software issues, and assisted 120+ students, staff, and faculty with technological needs.

Technology Analyst, Deutsche Bank; New York, NY

06/2019 - 08/2019

Built a simulator for messages sent between international credit/debit tracking systems in Java using Spring environment. In parallel, built and presented a sentiment analysis application focusing on public traded companies, their stocks, and media bias in Python using ML and NLP. Advocated for increased diversity in presentations and discussions.

Engineering Aide, Consolidated Edison, Inc.; New York, NY

07/2015 - 08/2017

- 05/2017 08/2017: Built test scripts and aided IT programmers in identifying algorithmic fallacies in OBIEE Performance Manager within Public Engineering.
- 09/2015 07/2016: Reviewed data filing for over 4000 work requests, organized data lists of employee review calls, and maintained documentation of ConEd facilities.
- 07/2015 09/2015: Reviewed conflicts of the energy grid, worked with external agencies, and compiled estimate cost data in Excel.

Skills

Programming Languages: Python, C/C++, Processing, Verilog, Java, Erlang, Go, and Matlab

Technical: Unix/Linux, Computer Security, Computer Systems, Sentiment Analysis, Digital Signal Processing, Test-Driven Development, User Experience Design, Human-Robot Interaction, and Computer Graphics

Research: GitHub repository mining, qualitative analysis, Grounded Theory, recruitment, interviewing, affinity diagrams, and literature reviews

Spoken Languages: English (Native), Serbo-Croatian (Native), French (Working)

Service UT-Austin iSchool Diversity and Inclusion Committee 08/2021 - Present

UT-Austin iSchool Undergraduate Studies Committee 08/2022 - Present

Hawaii International Conference on Systems Sciences (HICSS) 2022 - Reviewer

SIGBOVIK 2021 - Moderation Chair

Women in Cybersecurity (WiCyS) 2019 - Student Volunteer

Students Mentored Magali Astride Ngouabou Noubissi, graduated Pomona University 06/2020 - Present

Raaka Mukhopadhyay, student at Carnegie Mellon University. 01/2021 - 05/2021

Organizations iPride; UT-Austin 01/2022 - Present

International Student Union; CMU 02/2017 - 05/2020

Held the positions of President, Treasurer, and Secretary.

 Women in ECE; CMU
 09/2016 - 05/2020

 Society of Women Engineers; CMU
 09/2016 - 05/2020

 Girls Who Code; Brooklyn Technical High School
 09/2015 - 08/2016

Held the position of Mentor.

Travel Awards Amount Awarded:

International Conference of Software Engineering (ICSE) 2022 \$1200

Pittsburgh, PA, USA 2022

Vive la Différence Workshop 2022 - Research Software Engineers €1550

Lorentz Center, Leiden, NL 2022

References Associate Professor James Howison: howison@ischool.utexas.edu

Associate Professor Laura Dabbish: dabbish@cmu.edu